hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of Holo talk
for the week of February 22nd 1999 and
greetings from the cold and Frozen
Northeast part of the country we're
dipping down with wind chills to 20 to
degrees below zero this evening so it's
a cold one out there
Our Guest this week is Ron Olson from
laser Reflections and his Studio has
been doing post reflection holography of
live subjects for a number of years they
do absolutely gorgeous work and lawn's
going to come on to talk about his
studio and some of the projects and also
a book that he has coming up that he's
writing on this topic
upcoming guests we have Ron Kirk coming
up in the next few weeks and I've also
received the holographic CD that has a
holographic
music on it that we're going to get some
samples from and talk about holographic
sound as well that's another upcoming
show I had a few strange workshops this
week I had one gentleman come in for a
workshop for laser point or holography
who was from one of the largest research
corporations in the country in fact and
probably the world and he had told his
co-researchers about this guy in
Allentown Pennsylvania that was doing
laser pointer holography and they in
insisted that number one I was nuts that
he was wasting his time it wasn't
possible and another researcher said
theoretically it's just impossible to do
it but he came in made a beautiful
reflection hologram and he's going back
to his labs on Monday to show them that
also on other uh young men who came in
to take a workshop from New England he
drove down it was a nine hour drive but
he was doing it for his senior research
project and
um
I'll tell you something his Professor
told him straight out that it was
impossible to do Holograms using a laser
pointer or a laser diode and they were
pretty adamant about it
and he was listening he's been a
listener to the hollow talk show for uh
quite a long time and he says Frank if
you said it can be done I know it can be
done so I'm coming down to take a
workshop can I come down and make a
hologram and he left today in fact uh he
left around 1 30 2 o'clock this
afternoon and it's a little after eight
in the evening so he's not even home yet
he's got a long drive
and he's taking a really nice hologram
back of a Lamborghini that he did using
a laser pointer so there's a few people
that are in for surprises on Monday when
they find out that yes it is possible to
do holography using of the laser
pointers I got a few Holograms in from
Lonnie Anderson I think I'm pronouncing
that name pretty close to being correct
from Norway and I want to tell you folks
his Holograms are absolutely gorgeous I
sent Lonnie a laser pointer very early
on when we were just getting started and
I said to Ronnie look I need a few
people that can confirm that this works
and I need a few people that can say yes
you can do Holograms using laser pointer
and he was just thrilled to find out
that that the Holograms that he was
turning out looked as good as they did
so he said Frank I'm going to send you a
few and I was really looking forward to
looking at them and I want to tell you
something when I opened that box up and
I put those Holograms under the light my
jaw hit the table I could not believe
how gorgeous
absolutely gorgeous these Holograms were
using the
797.99 laser pointer just absolutely
incredible and yes that's the furnace
that you hear in the background kicking
on this this baby's been running around
the clock and it only shuts down for a
minute or two at a time and normally it
shuts down for a long period And I do
the recording during the shutdown
periods
we're just going to let that run tonight
because it's so cold I don't even want
to turn that off for a little bit just a
reminder I will be appearing at the 25th
anniversary Mensa conference being held
in central New Jersey at tynem Falls
holiday and Conference Center on
Saturday evening March the 6th and it's
a 10 admission to get in we're going to
bring some Holograms I'm going to give
the presentation on holography and laser
pointer holography specifically and also
close it out with a little laser light
show that was designed by a number of my
students over the years to the music of
the Boston Pops
so it's going to be a really nice time
on Saturday night March 6th okay let's
move on to our interview with Ron Olson
and I also have a link to his website
right on the whole top page so you want
to click on that link and visit his
website and see some of the beautiful
work that they're doing with the post
holography out in the San Francisco area
so I'm not going to come back on after
the interview is over so I will say
thank you for tuning in and hope that
you tune in each and every week for a
new topic new guest right here on the
internet's laser and holography talk
show hola talk this is Frankie Freitas
have a great week
would you like to make your own
one-of-a-kind hologram and learn how you
can start making holograms on your own
at the same time you can do this and
much more by attending one of
scientist's greatest in holography
workshops from beginner to Advanced
Frank's got a workshop that's just right
for you from single afternoon evening or
weekend introductory workshops to
Wednesday evening five week complete
courses and don't forget his newest
Workshop laser pointer holography locate
the Northeast Extension of the
Pennsylvania Turnpike and Interstate 78
the studio is a quick non-stop drive
from the New York Philadelphia and
Baltimore Washington DC areas for more
information call the Studio's toll-free
hotline at
1-800-458-3525 and begin your own
Journey with holography today that's
1-800-458-3525 for more information on
attending a Frankie greatest holography
Workshop today
foreign
I'm fine uh do you have a few minutes to
do the interview no problem okay uh
we're speaking to Ron Olson and I
believe you're in partnership with
Bernadette as well
that's correct and um why don't you tell
us a little bit about your studio and
what it is that you're doing out there
well laser reflection to it started
about uh I guess it's almost seven years
ago Frank uh with the goal of kind of
upgrading holography we uh my background
was in custom laser design
and uh laser Reflections took the early
position that
for whatever reason
holographers had kind of jointly
progressed down uh
kind of a dead end with respect to Ruby
lasers and I having built four of the
world's largest ruby laser uh new uh all
too well for inherent shortcomings
notably that the spatial quality of a
ruby laser required are the use of a
spatial filter and this was to be
avoided I felt at all costs but moreover
and kind of something that couldn't be
addressed technically uh the infrared
wavelength at 0.7 micro was
wholly inappropriate except for doing
things that were that the Ruby laser had
been designed to do things like tires
and guitar boxes and anything that
didn't have water in it this is a story
I'm repeating because giola tells it
often now
uh in my stat but uh if you put a flash
on your mouth you of course glow the
water in your skin absorbs all the long
wavelengths and you don't get a very
reflection if you if you tried that same
color of light and hit subjects with it
as a result I started asking myself well
what have I ever seen a holographic
portrait and the answer of course is
only in holographic exhibitions yeah so
this was kind of our impetus to get
going
I had again a custom laser design and I
found that there was some government
surplus Hardware
which I bought as a package and
reconfigured it lasers are very much
like stereo systems uh you start
amplifying until you you know you keep
amplifying until you run out of money or
you fill the room and in our case we
were trying to fill uh was not a room
with sound of course but a large plate
with light and we figured that with the
hardware uh kit that that I bought we
could fill roughly a one square meter
plate
so it turns out that uh that that really
wasn't uh my uh my appetite was somewhat
larger than was a commercially uh fed uh
we can't get plates quite as big as one
square meter but in fact as of this last
Monday we did our first recording on our
new large format size uh which is uh uh
purchased which we purchased and
actually are a dealer for I had
mentioned that to you Frank uh the
slavage materials and slavich now has a
60 by 80 centimeter plate and we did our
first transmission Master with that size
plate on Monday we're probably going to
hold off on doing reflection transfers
of said same for at least a month or two
the collimating or a converging mirror
that we have in our H2 setup we do
copies with this same Q Suite demium yag
laser and the the the collimating mirror
that we have is just a little bit too
small we have a 30 inch diameter mirror
and we're looking at purchasing a 36
inch mirror to do those larger transfers
we could actually just get by with the
mirror as is but it's a little small and
I think before we start doing a regular
basis we'd rather go with a larger optic
yeah it's an incredible scale it's
really nice for us because we we do
almost one-to-one images and a lot of
what we do and I had mentioned this to
you too a lot of what we sell right now
is either Boudoir portraiture or uh
yes and as it turns out most erotica
that we do of course people would like
to see a more of a person in a plate
rather than less yeah so for us with we
have a capability of doing about 20
reductions and this allows us to do
an adult woman seated in a plate so
you've already mentioned some of the
projects in fact I have a number of your
Holograms in my collection and there are
always people commenting on and that
they're the brightest and the clearest
Holograms they've ever seen I believe
they will thank you you shot the Masters
I believe and then maybe the Masters
went off to Hughes
um the photopolymer the story with us in
huge was that uh when Hughes became
aware of our work they decided that they
might get into art publishing so they
bought the rights to 13 of our early
image images which we had mastered when
we were in Felton the studios in its
Third location now we went from talking
to San Jose and now we're in downtown
San Francisco but Hughes had bought the
the rights to 13 of our images and in
fact uh
uh they were just learning how to make
very good qualities but when they
decided that this was not a profitable
business for Hughes and they got out of
it which was a shame there's now a a new
concern a new a new corporate entity uh
in in New Hampshire called RGB
holographics uh Paul cruzell and Jeff
Murray that are working together towards
kind of uh re-establishing the
photopolymer in display holography
that's not to say that people aren't
using photopolymer it's just that most
of them that are using it are using it
primarily uh shrink wrap telegraphy as I
tend to call for or security holography
so it doesn't really lend it up
neither one of a crystal holographics in
Utah isn't really concerned about making
uh display quality holographics of the
size that we need which is kind of
called by 16. yeah yeah now you also
mentioned in an email that you have a
book coming out well I'm writing a book
on based on the studio and really what
it's you know what what I tend to preach
Hank uh Ad nauseam probably but I tend
to preach a lot that that holography
should be looked at as something which
really does cost a lot of money good
holography for for commercial hologram
to survive requires a fair investment of
capital we have about three hundred
thousand dollars into our Imaging system
here at Laser Reflections and that's
that with uh with a lot of kind of
surplus government Parts if I Bernadette
and I are also Partners in a laser
company positive like which we started
about the same time we started laser
Reflections positive light makes high
energy lasers but it costs me more to
buy a a laser today that with my own
company uh than it did 20 years ago
these high energy solid state lasers
like ours
it's like buying a Ford Taurus if there
were only 50 made a year it's going to
cost you a good sum of money yeah now
there are things that are that are
happening uh perhaps in almost real time
uh friends in geola in Lithuania are
starting to Market Hardware
to do holography and this is a
technically it looks like a very good
system uh just on paper I haven't worked
with the system but I've seen the images
and certainly uh these are are
comparable to to what we do and that
system I think they will retail for
something under a hundred thousand
dollars I think between for the small
laser it might be somewhere closer to 60
and for the large one something around a
hundred thousand dollars but this is the
kind of investment that I tell people
that they really need to think about
making if they're serious about doing
holography and when I say serious about
doing holography I mean real-time
commercial holography yeah we have on a
day on a good day at Laser Reflections
we can do up to 10 16 by 24 inch Masters
and and up to half a dozen of copies one
each of six different Masters this is
that for two people in the studio this
is what Bernadette and I can do and I
tell people that that if you if you
can't do this
in working with artists if the projects
take too long
interest when we bring our directors in
here we can shoot and we don't have to
this is not a White Knuckle technology
at this point this is did we get the
right image not did we get the uh you
know did the laser fire yeah this kind
of stuff it has to go and and the book
that I'm writing is is basically going
to tell that story that the holography
has progressed to a point now where with
an investment you can be uh a productive
commercial holographer feeding markets
in display advertising in wall art in
decorative art and in retail displays
and and this is and and Museum displays
these are
these are that we're working on very
hard at Laser Reflections and and we see
the market for for high quality display
holography as being really huge it's
really amazing to me how few people uh
perhaps seeing that the potential for
holography but if you look at a large
format a reflection or transmission
hologram there's not too too many people
who would argue that it's visibly
visually the the most impressive uh
Imaging technique going exactly now this
book will be available once it's
published on your website people will be
able to order it it sure will be okay
and we will have a link in fact there is
a link if you're listening to the show
right now right on the whole talk page
that will go to laser Reflections
homepage I would suggest you go over
there and see some of the gorgeous work
that you're doing why don't you talk a
little bit about this Boudoir and the
erotica images that you're doing how did
that's a very big contract how did you
land that well no it's
we started doing it was one of those
things right when we designed designed
this laser we went backwards from skin
and that's where we we saw the failing
of people who were trying to image uh
using infrared or Ruby lasers uh we just
uh we went backwards since if we had the
idea Imaging system it would be green
light with uh X Co where X is about two
meters and uh and and short exposures so
we wouldn't have to worry about
vibration something on the order of 15
nanoseconds
as it turns out that's that's really uh
our combination of green light the agfa
or vrpm uh from Slavic remote uh that
that combination is great for doing skin
and eyes so right away we started doing
uh people and uh people kept telling us
uh you know you should you should focus
more on the on the nudes and on the
erotica because it's this is what's
really going to get attention and
they're right in that we did a lot of of
large animal images that I'm extremely
proud of and the Bernadette and I did
over the last three or four years we did
around
chimpanzees and we did the entire
collection of raptors from the Lindsay
Museum all their Birds of Prey we did a
mountain lion we did a link all from
live subjects all brought to our studio
they're beautiful but uh very few people
buy them and at the same time what do
you think that is I think it has to do
with just the fact that uh uh what we'll
need for the animal images to take off
to get sponsored shows I think they
don't advertise well they don't show
well and I think that if you're going to
buy something sight unseen you probably
won't buy an image of a cougar but
you're much more likely to buy the image
of a woman's backside and I think it's
it that's the the long shot of it is
that the uh the eroticus cells it's like
in in a lot of things uh skin tends to
sell much before anything else and I
think for the rest of the decorative art
to catch on uh the the erotica will
catch on first that's it's just going to
be a kind of a a natural sequence of
events I think that the animals will
sell them it's not like we're not
shooting them we've got three monkeys uh
we have a friend who's a wildlife
trainer here in the Bay Area and he can
get us access to almost any animals we
want we're right now designing a cage
a glass cage so that we can safely image
large cats and large canines like wolves
and we expect to be doing those images
at the end of 1999. we had a Siberian
tiger here 472 pound tiger right to the
door but we were having so much problem
with controlling the cougar the mountain
lion that we said uh let's let's put
this off and we're now redesigning a
cage but I think that's just natural I
think once the work gets seen a lot of
the animal images will sell we continue
to invest in them but the erotic is much
easier and a lot more venues for us to
sell the erotica we go to erotica art
shows
to Las Vegas signage shows we we do a
lot of nightclub type shows and
Nightclub environments and bar owners
are very comfortable with our with our
nodes in erotica and when you think
about it who's going to buy the the
collections of animals
it's much more difficult to point a
finger at a targeted Market
is the book going to be an instructional
book or just sort of like a history of
your company the book's going to be
instructional but the book's going to be
instructional in it in our kind of way
of holography how you really light
subjects and and not how you make a
hologram so to speak you know we're
we're going to show our setup but then
we're going to explain the the the the
the kind of subtleties of the of the
holographic technique as as we have
learned it
and the darkroom technique uh this is
going to assume that you have 100
megawatt laser that's that's the initial
assumption that we make you see you've
got a laser fairly comparable to to ours
and then you want to make images with it
so we're not talking about laser pointer
holography here you're right no this is
a this is a big deal but we tell people
and I and I I'm not at all shy about it
if you want to get into a photo
developing a one-hour photo developing
shop you you have to invest in quite a
bit of Hardware you can still do things
in the old-fashioned way you know you
can take trays and develop plates one at
a time but if you're not careful uh
you're going to look around and you're
not going to be competitive with people
who have better Hardware yeah the laser
photography remark brings up this
question there's a lot of kids that
listen to this show that really love
holography and especially the time that
this show is going to air which is in
the next week or two because there's a
lot of science projects going on and
taking into account that you have a very
successful business and you're a very
astute business person would you have
any message for the kids say that
they're you've got an eight-year-old uh
not an a year old but an eighth grader
out there that runs holography and the
top thing that they'd like to do is grow
up and do holography what message would
you have for a kid in eighth grade right
now who would like to grow up and get
into the field of holography well the
message I would have for a kid in the
eighth grade is the same message that I
I would give to college students when
I'm asked to to kind of fill in here and
there and that is that there's a
fantastic opportunity for for
within the graphic arts industry
holography has been a classic
underachiever but its time is at hand
and you know I just cite the the the
coming of change in the retail
environment and and the museum
environment the the moves towards more
interactive exhibitory and the fact that
what we're really showing is in fact
high resolution imaging in a day when
people talk so much about high
resolution TV and this and that we're
talking about several orders of
magnitude higher resolution images than
can be produced through any photographic
technique and for me
this is really some of the excitement of
holography and careers in holography
right now couple this with the fact that
Laser Technology like ours which for
years have been uh
uh very much uh uh kind of almost black
magic I think the reputation I had for
for years Frank and why people were
putting our studio down in terms of the
concept was so I was the only guy to
make this work you know sure I played
you know with ledgers for 20 years but
if you if you're not you know if you
don't want to play with lasers like like
Ron does uh you can't do it but not the
case anymore and we're finding that that
young people coming through various
different programs in college whether it
be mechanical engineering electrical
engineering physics chemistry uh uh
medical training uh the the medical
Sciences are using high energy lasers
now and we're finding that we see a lot
of young people come out of college with
a very good background in in high energy
lasers this is not just Stanford and
Harvard and you know Penn State these
days this is you can go in onto any
college campus in this country and find
high energy lasers at work
and as they these kids get trained as
they come out of school they're they're
very Adept laser operators now there's
the the other thing in conjunction with
that is the fact that because the Laser
Technology itself is evolving we're
finding that most of of the older
hardware and I remind people that our
laser hardware and our system is Circa
1978. for holography it really hasn't
changed though the holography the the
the light requirements for doing single
color holography like we do have not
change the hardware package is basically
the same so as many Sciences obsolete
lasers like ours may be available in a
secondary market so now you have the
combination of skilled trained laser
operators at the University level and
second-hand equipment coming available
on the market for pennies on the dollar
this then makes for for Studios like
ours to be a reality
it's what we at Ledger Reflections are
going to look to do is to build a number
of studios around the country of where
we can hire trained laser operators who
will then we hope have a great careers
in holography
well why do you have any closing
comments or any remarks you'd like to
make to the listeners before we head out
here no just if you if and when they're
in San Francisco to come and visit our
studio we'll write down we're a block
from the Museum of Modern Art and two
blocks from the Moscone Center okay Ron
I want to thank you very much for taking
the time I know you have to be very busy
for coming on the show well you're most
welcome Frank get a chance log on and
listen to it for sure okay all right
thank you very much you're welcome